<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 ead.xsd" relatedencoding="MARC21">
	<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" audience="internal" findaidstatus="edited-full-draft"
		repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601"
		scriptencoding="iso15924">
		<eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-tx">urn:taro:tslac.30156 <!-- For this file to pass compliance checker the name of the file must be changed to 30156 --></eadid>
		<filedesc>
			<titlestmt>
				<titleproper>Texas School for the Blind and Visually Impaired:</titleproper>
				<subtitle>An Inventory of School for the Blind and Visually Impaired Meeting Files
					at the Texas State Archives
				</subtitle>
				<author>Finding aid by Tony Black and Anna M. Reznik</author>
				<sponsor encodinganalog="536$a">This EAD finding aid was created in cooperation with
					Texas Archival Resources Online.</sponsor>
			</titlestmt>
			<publicationstmt>
				<publisher>Texas State Library and Archives Commission</publisher>
				<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian" normal="2015">June 2015</date>
			</publicationstmt>
		</filedesc>
		<profiledesc>
			<creation>Finding aid encoded by Tony Black in EAD Version 2002 as part of the TARO
				project, <date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 2008.</date>
			</creation>
			<langusage>Finding aid written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn"
					>English.</language></langusage>
			<descrules>Description based on <emph render="italic">DACS</emph>.</descrules>
		</profiledesc>
		<!-- Add a new change for each major revision of the finding aid, include what was done, who did it, and when -->
		<revisiondesc>
			<change>
				<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 2015.</date>
				<item>Revised by Anna M. Reznik,</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June 2015.</date>
				<item>Revised by Anna M. Reznik,</item>
			</change>
		</revisiondesc>
	</eadheader>
	<archdesc level="subgrp" type="inventory" audience="external">
		<!--{Be sure level attribute is correct.}-->
		<did>
			<head>Overview</head>
			<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
				<extref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
					xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://www.tsl.state.tx.us/arc/index.html"
					xlink:type="simple">Texas State Archives</extref></repository>
			<origination label="Creator:">
				<corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Texas School for the Blind and
					Visually Impaired.</corpname>
			</origination>
			<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245">School for the Blind and Visually
				Impaired meeting files</unittitle>
			<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive" era="ce"
				calendar="gregorian" normal="1856/1919">1856-1919, </unitdate> 
			<unitdate label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive" era="ce"
				calendar="gregorian" normal="1979/1919">1979-2015</unitdate>
			<unitid label="OCLC Record No.:" encodinganalog="099" countrycode="US"
				repositorycode="US-tx">ocn952118254</unitid>
			<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">The Texas School for the Blind and
				Visually Impaired is a public school district that provides specialized services
				that focus on the learning needs of primary and secondary students with visual
				impairments, including those with additional disabilities. Records include agenda,
				minutes, and agenda attachments of meetings of the board of trustees and date from
				1856 to 1919 and 1979 to 2015. Subjects include the results of student testing,
				administration of the school district, employee benefits and expectations, support
				activities for blind and visually impaired students, and various school district
				policies.</abstract>
			<langmaterial label="Language:" encodinganalog="546$a">These materials are written
				predominately in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language> with
				scattered <language langcode="spa" scriptcode="Latn">Spanish</language>
				throughout.</langmaterial>
			<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>9.3 cubic
				ft.</extent></physdesc>
		</did>
		<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
			<head>Restrictions on Access</head>
			<p>Materials do not circulate, but may be used in the State Archives search room.
				Materials will be retrieved from and returned to storage areas by staff members.</p>
		</accessrestrict>
		<userestrict encodinganalog="540">
			<head>Restrictions on Use</head>
			<p>Most records created by Texas state agencies are not copyrighted. State records also
				include materials received by, not created by, state agencies. Copyright remains
				with the creator. The researcher is responsible for complying with U.S. Copyright
				Law (Title 17 U.S.C.).</p>
		</userestrict>
		<phystech encodinganalog="340">
			<head>Technical Requirements</head>
			<p>None.</p>
		</phystech>
		<bioghist encodinganalog="545">
			<head>Agency History</head>
			<p>The Texas School for the Blind and Visually Impaired (TSBVI) was established by the
				6th Texas Legislature as the Asylum for the Blind (Chapter CVIII, August 16, 1856).
				In January 1857, the first student was admitted to the institution. The first
				classes of students met in a rented residence in Austin. The Asylum for the Blind
				eventually moved into a building on 19th Street and East Avenue. This site was
				transferred to the University of Texas in 1925, becoming the <emph
					render="doublequote">Little Campus.</emph> The Asylum for the Blind became known
				as the Texas Institution for the Blind (also referred to as the Blind Institute) in
				1905 and the Texas School for the Blind in 1915. In this latter year, the
				legislature appropriated funds to build a new campus on 73 acres of land in
				northwest Austin, donated by the citizens. This land, located at 1100 West 45th
				Street, was occupied by the school in 1917. In 1919, the 36th Legislature created
				the Board of Control (Senate Bill 147, Regular Session). This three-member board
				replaced the boards of governors of each of the state's eleemosynary institutions,
				including the board of trustees of the School for the Blind. In 1951, the 52nd
				Legislature placed the School for the Blind under the Board for Texas State
				Hospitals and Special Schools (House Bill 378, Regular Session). The 53rd
				Legislature transferred the School for the Blind to the State Board of Education
				(Senate Bill 119/House Bill 128, Regular Session). In 1965, the legislature placed
				the School for the Blind under the direction of a Central Services Agency for
				Special Schools for the Blind and the Deaf, under the State Board of Education,
				which became the Texas Education Agency (House Bill 377, 59th Legislature, Regular
				Session). The name of the School for the Blind was changed in 1989 to the TSBVI to
				better reflect the population it serves. The TSBVI is an independent school
				district, which covers kindergarten through twelfth grade education, and provides
				residential services for the blind and multihandicapped blind students. TSBVI also
				provides technical assistance to teachers, other professionals, and parents in local
				Texas communities to better serve blind and visually impaired students in the
				students' home districts.</p>
			<p>Concurrently, visually-impaired African American youths were taught at a similar
				institution. In 1887, the 20th Legislature created the Texas Institute for Deaf,
				Dumb and Blind Colored Youths, to occupy a 100-acre tract four miles northwest of
				the State Capitol, just east of what became Camp Mabry (House Bill 445, 20th
				Legislature, Regular Session). The first class had nine blind students and eight
				deaf students, taught by one teacher apiece. Enrollment had climbed to 125 by 1912,
				with a faculty of 11. The governing body was a three-person board of trustees. In
				1930, orphans began to be admitted to the newly designated Deaf, Dumb and Blind
				Asylum for Colored Youths and Colored Orphans (House Bill 154, 41st Legislature, 5th
				Called Session). Three more name changes followed: in 1943, to the State School for
				Deaf and Blind Negro Children; in 1947, to the Texas Blind, Deaf and Orphan School;
				and in 1965, to the Texas Blind and Deaf School (finally placed under the Texas
				Education Agency). With desegregation in 1966, black students were merged with white
				students in the TSBVI and the Texas School for the Deaf.</p>
			<p>The TSBVI is overseen by a nine-member board appointed by the governor for
				overlapping six-year terms. Public meetings of the board are held five to six times
				per year. Three of the members must be blind or visually impaired, three must be
				parents of blind or visually impaired persons, and three must have had experience in
				working with the blind or visually impaired. The board is the equivalent of the
				board of trustees of an independent school district: it appoints an executive
				director or superintendent to administer the school, and all actions of the board
				may be appealed to the State Board of Education (Texas Education Code, Sections
				11.06 through 11.091). The board has three standing committees: audit, compliance,
				and management review; finance; and programs.</p>
			<p>(Sources include: <emph render="italic">Guide to Texas State Agencies</emph>, 11th
				edition (2001); James W. Markham and Paulette Delahoussaye, <extref
					xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new"
					xlink:actuate="onRequest"
					xlink:href="https://tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/kct25">"Texas School
					for the Blind and Visually Impaired,"</extref>
				<emph render="italic"> Handbook of Texas Online</emph>; and TSBVI's website (<extref
					xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new"
					xlink:actuate="onRequest" xlink:href="http://www.tsbvi.edu"
					>http://www.tsbvi.edu</extref>), all accessed June 30, 2015.)</p>
		</bioghist>
		<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$b">
			<head>Scope and Contents of the Records</head>
			<p>The Texas School for the Blind and Visually Impaired is a public school district that
				provides specialized services that focus on the unique learning needs of primary and
				secondary students with visual impairments, including those with additional
				disabilities. Records consist of agenda, minutes and agenda attachments (including
				reports, correspondence, policies, and directives) for the meetings of the board of
				trustees and date from 1856 to 1919 and 1979 to 2015. Subjects include the results
				of student testing, administration of the school district, employee benefits and
				expectations, support activities for blind and visually impaired students attending
				school in his or her home district, staff policies (leave time and rights),
				education policies, and student discipline and welfare policies. Earlier minutes,
				dating 1856-1919, apparently complete for the first 64 years of the school's
				existence, are handwritten for the 19th century, and typewritten and pasted into the
				ledger for the early 20th century. In addition to minutes, these earlier minutes
				contain regulations, duties, and inventories of property. Agenda inform the public
				as to what will be discussed and/or decided at each meeting. Minutes document in a
				thorough but summary fashion the official actions of the board in its meetings.
				Researchers should note that minutes are approved at the following meeting, so
				records document the business of the previous meeting.</p>
			<p>To prepare this inventory, the described materials were cursorily reviewed to
				delineate series, to confirm the accuracy of contents lists, to provide an estimate
				of dates covered, and to determine record types.</p>
		</scopecontent>
		<arrangement encodinganalog="351">
			<head>Arrangement of the Records</head>
			<p>These records are arranged in chronological order.</p>
		</arrangement>
		<controlaccess>
			<head>Index Terms</head>
			<p><emph render="italic">The terms listed here were used to catalog the records. The
					terms can be used to find similar or related records.</emph></p>
			<controlaccess>
				<head>Corporate Names:</head>
				<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="710">Texas School for the Blind.</corpname>
				<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="710">Texas State Asylum for the
					Blind.</corpname>
				<corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="710">Texas Institution for the
					Blind.</corpname>
			</controlaccess>
			<controlaccess>
				<head>Subjects:</head>
				<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Blind--Education--Texas.</subject>
				<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Blind--Institutional
					care--Texas.</subject>
				<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Blind
					children--Education--Texas.</subject>
				<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Blind children--Institutional
					care--Texas.</subject>
			</controlaccess>
			<controlaccess>
				<head>Document Types:</head>
				<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Minutes (administrative
					records)--Texas--Blind--1856-1919, 1979-2015.</genreform>
				<genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655">Agendas (administrative
					records)--Texas--Blind--1979-2015.</genreform>
			</controlaccess>
			<controlaccess>
				<head>Functions:</head>
				<function source="aat" encodinganalog="657">Teaching the blind and visually
					impaired.</function>
			</controlaccess>
		</controlaccess>
		<relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1">
			<head>Related Material</head>
			<p><emph render="italic">The following materials are offered as possible sources of
					further information on the agencies and subjects covered by the records. The
					listing is not exhaustive. </emph></p>
			<relatedmaterial>
				<p><repository><emph render="bold">Texas State Archives</emph></repository></p>
				<archref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
					xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
					xlink:href="http://www.lib.utexas.edu/taro/tslac/10207/tsl-10207.html">Texas
					School for the Blind records, 1871-1989, 14.71 cubic ft.</archref>
				<archref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
					xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
					xlink:href="http://www.lib.utexas.edu/taro/tslac/50074/tsl-50074.html">Texas
					Commission for the Blind records, 1932-2003, undated, 19.75 cubic ft.</archref>
				<archref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
					xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
					xlink:href="http://www.lib.utexas.edu/taro/tslac/20062/tsl-20062.html">Texas
					State Board of Control, Records, 1854, 1885-1890, 1909-1979, undated (bulk
					1935-1953), 103.47 cubic ft.</archref>
				<archref xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
					xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
					xlink:href="http://www.lib.utexas.edu/taro/tslac/90027/tsl-90027.html"
					>Blueprints and drawings collection, 1854-1984, undated, 41.21 cubic. ft. [See
					series Texas School for the Blind and Visually Impaired, 1902-1903, 1911-1912,
					undated; and Fireproofing and Fire Protection, 1896, 1912-1913,
					undated.]</archref>
			</relatedmaterial>
		</relatedmaterial>
		<descgrp>
			<prefercite encodinganalog="524">
				<head>Preferred Citation</head>
				<p>(Identify the item), Texas School for the Blind and Visually Impaired meeting
					files. Archives and Information Services Division, Texas State Library and
					Archives Commission.</p>
			</prefercite>
			<acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
				<head>Accession Information</head>
				<p>Accession numbers: 1989/073, 1998/115, 1999/012, 2000/053, 2001/037, 2002/068,
					2003/045, 2004/026, 2005/053, 2006/013, 2007/014, 2008/075, 2009/030, 2010/079,
					2011/006, 2011/343, 2011/344, 2012/007, 2013/010, 2014/011, 2015/024,
					2015/224</p>
				<p>These records were transferred to the Archives and Information Services Division
					of the Texas State Library and Archives Commission by the Texas School for the
					Blind on December 14, 1988; by the Texas School for the Blind and Visually
					Impaired on May 19 and September 29, 1998; October 29, 1999; October 18, 2000;
					November 7, 2001; October 21, 2002; September 29, 2003; October 28, 2004;
					September 15, 2005; September 15, 2006; January 22 and September 24, 2008; March
					3 and September 13, 2010; September 15, 2011; September 13, 2012; September 16,
					2013; and October 2, 2014; and by the Legislative Reference Library on February
					17, 2011 and December 13, 2012.</p>
			</acqinfo>
			<altformavail encodinganalog="530">
				<head>Other Formats for the Records</head>
				<p>The School for the Blind and Visually Imparied maintains current and archived
					minutes and agenda on its website (<extref
						xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple"
						xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
						xlink:href="http://www.tsbvi.edu/board-of-trustees-info-and-minutes-items"
						>http://www.tsbvi.edu/board-of-trustees-info-and-minutes-items</extref>).</p>
			</altformavail>
			<originalsloc encodinganalog="535">
				<head>Location of Originals</head>
				<p>The record copies of meeting agenda and minutes are maintained by the Texas
					School for the Blind and Visually Impaired.</p>
			</originalsloc>
			<accruals encodinganalog="584">
				<head>Accruals</head>
				<p>The Texas School for the Blind and Visually Impaired transfers copies of meeting
					records to the Texas State Archives regularly.</p>
			</accruals>
			<processinfo encodinganalog="583">
				<head>Processing Information</head>
				<p>Minutes from Agency minutes project processed by Tony Black, March 1998</p>
				<p>New accessions added by Tony Black, May 1998, September 1998, October 1999,
					October 2000, November 2001, October 2002, September 2003, October 2004,
					September 2005, September 2006, and January 2008</p>
				<p>Finding aid encoded by Tony Black in EAD Version 2002, May 2008</p>
				<p>New accessions added by Tony Black, September 2008, March 2010</p>
				<p>Updates to description, DACS-compliance, and six new accessions added by Anna M.
					Reznik, June 2015</p>
				<p>Minutes removed from the TSBVI records finding aid and added to this inventory by
					Anna M. Reznik, September 2015</p>
			</processinfo>
		</descgrp>
		<dsc type="combined">
			<head>Detailed Description of the Records</head>
			<c01 level="series" id="ser1">
				<did>
					<unittitle>Texas School for the Blind and Visually Impaired meeting files, </unittitle>
					<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" type="inclusive">1856-1919, 1979-2015, </unitdate>
					<physdesc><extent>9.3 cubic ft.</extent></physdesc>
				</did>
				<c02>
					<did>
						<unittitle><emph render="bold">Texas State Asylum for the Blind/Blind
								Institute/Texas School for the Blind,</emph>
						</unittitle>
						<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold"
							>1856-1919</emph></unitdate>
					</did>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Volume">1989/073-28</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" type="inclusive">1856 thru
								1899</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Volume">1989/073-29</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" type="inclusive">1900 thru
								1918</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Volume">1989/073-30</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian" type="inclusive">1918 thru
								1919</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
				</c02>
				<c02>
					<did>
						<unittitle><emph render="bold">Texas School for the Blind, </emph>
						</unittitle>
						<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold"
							>1979-1989</emph></unitdate>
					</did>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 1979, January and
								November 1980, and November 1983</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January thru November
								1982</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January thru November
								1983</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March thru November
								1984</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">October 1985 thru November
								1987</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">2011/343</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January thru November
								1988</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">2011/343</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January thru March
								1989</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">June and November 1989 and March
								1990</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
				</c02>
				<c02>
					<did>
						<unittitle><emph render="bold">Texas School for the Blind and Visually
								Impaired, </emph>
						</unittitle>
						<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian"><emph render="bold"
							>1989-2015</emph></unitdate>
					</did>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 1989 thru March
								1990</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">2011/343</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1990</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">2011/343</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 1990</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 1990</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">2011/343</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September 1990</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">November 1990</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">2011/343</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">January 1991</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">March 1991</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">1998/115-1</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">May 1991</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<c03>
						<did>
							<container type="Box">2011/343</container>
							<unitdate era="ce" calendar="gregorian">September thru November
								1991</unitdate>
						</did>
					</c03>
					<!-- 
This series has subsequent <c03> levels that were limited here to save on length for the purposes of the TARO encoding guidelines, June 2016.

-->
				</c02>
			</c01>
		</dsc>
	</archdesc>
</ead>
